Guide to the Paul Moritz Warburg Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Paul Moritz Warburg papers
1904-1932
MS 535
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.5
Correspondence, documents, memorabilia, and printed materials relating to the career of Paul M. Warburg in banking and international finance. Correspondents include Nelson Aldrich, Carter Glass, Col. Edward M. House and Woodrow Wilson.
Warburg, Paul M. (Paul Moritz), 1868-1932
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James P. Warburg, 1959.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence, 1904-1932. II. Topical files, 1911-1956. III. Scrapbooks, 1910-1932.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Paul M. Warburg, recently presented to the University Library by his son James P. Warburg, contain approximately 5,000 pieces of manuscript covering the period 1904-1932. The collection consists of official and private correspondence, documents, drafts of Warburg's many writings, materials relating to war-financing and the Federal Reserve System, scrapbooks, memorabilia, and 169 volumes on banking and finance. The papers as a whole present an excellent documentation of the economic history of the United States during the period preceding World War I and of the decade which followed that catastrophe, providing as well a record of the great services which Paul Warburg rendered the nation. It appears fitting that this material should join the papers already at Yale of Colonel Edward M. House, Henry L. Stimson, William Kent, Frank Polk, and Senator Francis G. Newlands, men in public life whose careers covered roughly the same period as that of Paul Warburg's participation in national affairs.
Warburg's correspondents were those who were helping to shape the tenor of the times, and the files are replete with such names as Jane Addams, Nelson Aldrich, Bernard Baruch, Sir Ernest Cassel, Sir Austin Chamberlain, Josephus Daniels, John W. Davis, Norman Davis, Carter Glass, E. H. Harriman, Herbert Hoover, Lord Keynes, Henry Cabot Lodge, William McAdoo, Andrew Mellon, John D. Rockefeller, Reid Smoot, and Lillian Wald. Banking, the economic growth of the country, the course of the war, and the ensuing peace, all came within the scope of Warburg's interest. Many individuals solicited his advice upon matters ranging from the Liberty Bond drives to the question of what to do with a defeated Germany.
Born (1868) into an old Hamburg banking family, Paul Warburg came to the United States in 1902 as a member of Kuhn, Loeb and Company. In the succeeding decade he familiarized himself so thoroughly with the American financial situation that he rapidly became an authority in domestic banking policy. This, combined with his intimate knowledge of European finance and his personal acquaintance with the leading figures in international banking, placed him in a unique position one which caused his pronouncements and writings to be received with singular respect.
Excerpted from Howard B. Gotlieb, "Architect of Federal Reserve: The Papers of Paul Moritz Warburg," The Yale University Library Gazette, 35, no. 3 (January 1961), pp. 106-110.
Biographical / Historical
Paul M. Warburg (1868-1932): member of Kuhn, Loeb & Co., N.Y., until appointed member of Federal Reserve Board, 1914-1918; member of U.S. Section International High Commission, 1917; chairman of the board of International Acceptance Bank, N. Y., and of The Manhattan Company; director of B & O Railroad, Western Union Telegraph Co., several other corporations.
Banks and banking -- United States; Business; International finance; World War, 1914-1918; New York (State) -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Bankers; Addams, Jane, 1860-1935; Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth), 1841-1915; Andrew, A. Piatt (Abram Piatt), 1873-1936; Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965; Calder, William Musgrave, 1869-1945; Chamberlain, Austen, Sir, 1863-1937; Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948; Davis, John W. (John William), 1873-1955; Davis, Norman H. (Norman Hezekiah), 1878-1944; Gassel, Ernest, Sir, 1852-1921; Glass, Carter, 1858-1946; Hand, Learned, 1872-1961; Harding, W. P. G. (William Proctor Gould), 1864-1930; Harrison, Edward Henry, 1848-1909; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, Jr., 1841-1935; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; House, Edward Mandell, 1858-1938; Houston, David Franklin, 1866-1940; Kellogg, Frank B. (Frank Billings), 1856-1937; Keynes, John Maynard, 1883-1946; Knox, Philander C. (Philander Chase), 1853-1921; Lane, Franklin K.; Leffingwell, R. C. (Russell Cornell), 1878-1960; McAdoo, W. G. (William Gibbs), 1863-1941; Mellon, Andrew W. (Andrew William), 1855-1937; Mills, Ogden Livingston, 1884-1937; Morgenthau, Henry, 1856-1946; Morrow, Dwight W. (Dwight Whitney), 1873-1931; Norton, Charles Dyer, 1871-1922; Phillips, William, 1878-1968; Rockefeller, John D., Jr. (John Davison), 1874-1960; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937; Rowe, L. S. (Leo Stanton), 1871-1946; Schiff, Jacob H. (Jacob Henry), 1847-1920; Schiff, Mortimer L., 1877-1931; Smoot, Reed, 1862-1941; Strong, Benjamin, 1872-1928; Tumulty, Joseph P. (Joseph Patrick), 1879-1954; Warburg, James P. (James Paul), 1896-1969; Warburg, Paul M. (Paul Moritz), 1868-1932; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Woodrow, William Hartman, 1868-1934; Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System (U.S.); Kuhn, Loeb & Company
- Correspondence, 1904-1932, Series I
  - 1904-1914 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 15)
  - 1914 May 5-1915 (Box 2, Folder 16 - 29)
  - 1916-1917 Feb (Box 3, Folder 30 - 42)
  - 1917 Mar-1919 Aug (Box 4, Folder 43 - 58)
  - 1919 Sep-1932 Jan 26 (Box 5, Folder 59 - 74)
  - 1932 Jan 26-Feb, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 75 - 80)
- Topical files, 1911-1956, Series II
  - Aldrich plan, 1911, 1914, undated (Box 7, Folder 81 - 82)
  - Banking and currency reform: U.S. Congressional hearings, 1913 (Box 7, Folder 83 - 84)
  - Chronology, 1907-1914 (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Clippings, 1910-1929, undated (Box 7, Folder 86 - 89)
  - Diary, 1915 (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Europe, post-war, 1919, undated (Box 7, Folder 91 - 92)
  - European memorandum, 1919-1920, undated (Box 7, Folder 93 - 95)
  - European memorandum, undated (Box 8, Folder 96)
  - Federal Reserve System
    - General, 1914-1918 (Box 8, Folder 97-105)
    - Creation and suggested changes, 1909-1917, undated (Box 8, Folder 106 - 107)
    - Organization, 1912, 1914 (Box 8, Folder 108 - 109)
    - Certificates (Box 17)
  - Germany, undated (Box 9, Folder 110)
  - History of the Bankers' Acceptances Regulation, 1914-1915 (Box 9, Folder 111 - 116)
  - Memorabilia, 1918, undated (Box 9, Folder 117)
  - Printed material, 1908-1920 (Box 9, Folder 118 - 121)
  - Printed material, 1921-1927, undated (Box 10, Folder 122 - 123)
  - War finance, 1917-1918 (Box 10, Folder 124 - 127)
  - Warburg, James P.: family history and photographs, 1955-1956, undated (Box 10, Folder 128)
  - Writings, 1907-1910 (Box 10, Folder 129 - 130)
  - Writings, 1911-1929, undated (Box 11, Folder 131 - 138)
- Scrapbooks, 1910-1932, Series III
  - 1910 (Box 12, Folder 139)
  - 1914 (Box 12, Folder 140)
  - 1914 (Box 13, Folder 141)
  - 1914-1915 (Box 14, Folder 142)
  - 1918 (Box 14, Folder 143)
  - 1930 (Box 15, Folder 144)
  - 1932 (Box 15, Folder 145)
  - 1932 (Box 16, Folder 146)